Find the Empress
황후를 찾아가야지
The matter of Prince of Jin's misfortune
진왕의 일은 아직 아는 사람이 적어서
I, as a daughter-in-law
며느리가 모후를 뵙는 걸
Might not be stopped
막을 사람은 없을 걸세
Though the Empress never interferes in court matters
정사에 간섭 안 하는 황후라지만
She must care for her son
아들 일은 상관할 걸세
Indeed
맞습니다
At this time
지금으로선
I'm afraid only the Empress can delay Prince of Ning
황후만이 영왕의 발목을 잡을 수 있을 거예요
Perhaps
어쩌면
Chancellor Chen was right
진 승상이 옳았는지도 모르지
Sir
대, 대인
Rash and hasty
뭔데 이리 호들갑이야
Rushing to be reborn
빨리 죽고 싶은 거냐!
Sir
대인!
Your Highness
전하!
Empress
황후께서...
This palace's rashness
내가 호들갑 떨었구먼
Must have made Sir Chen laugh
부끄럽게 됐네, 진 대인
Empress, Mother
- 황후마마 - 모후
How dare you
어떻게 감히...
Beat my son like this
내 아들을 이런 꼴로 만들 수가 있어!
Prince
왕야
Release him immediately
어서 내려놓지 못하겠느냐!
Hurry
어서 빨리!
Everyone, leave first
모두 나가거라
Mother
모후
Aren't you leaving?
안 나가고 뭐 하느냐?
Waiting for me to scold you?
혼나기를 기다리는 거냐?
You might as well scold me to vent your anger
차라리 절 한 번 호되게 꾸짖어 주세요
Get out
당장 나가!
Yes
예
Prince
왕야
I came too late
제가 늦었어요
You three men
부자 셋이
Are like pressing down a gourd and a ladle pops up
어쩜 이리 바람 잘 날이 없느냐
None of you let me rest easy
하나같이 내 속만 태우는구나
Just watched your father take medicine
방금 폐하가 약 드시는 것을 보고 왔는데
And now you two brothers
돌아서니 너희 형제는
Are fighting like this
이 난리를 벌이고 있고
I don't understand your schemes
너희들의 복잡한 속사정은 모르겠지만
You and your elder brother
너와 네 형 모두 이 어미의 피붙이다
Sometimes
가끔은 말이다
I feel like a porter
이 어미는 마치 짐꾼 같다고 느낀단다
Must balance both ends of the carrying pole
양쪽 다 챙겨야 하고
Can't favor either side
어느 쪽 하나 치우칠 수도 없어
Father's health
부황의 건강은
Is it alright?
어떠신가요?
You know
너도 알지 않느냐
Your father usually
평소에도 단약을 달고 사는 분이시다
His health was already poor
몸이 원래 좋지 않았는데
With this trouble
이번 일까지 겹치니
He's been bedridden for days again
며칠째 침상에서 일어나지도 못하신다
Your father doesn't want to see you now
지금은 너를 보기 싫다 하시니
If you have something to say
하고 싶은 말이 있으면
I'll say it for you
어미가 대신 가서 말해 주마
Thank you, Mother
감사합니다, 모후
Please tell Father
부디 부황께 이렇게 전해주세요